The sound of a train running alongside a river
The color of sunflowers blooming facing down
The sunset becomes a striped border
Why do I want to cry every time you say "thank you"?
I'm like a child
I thought I'd left all my tears in the fridge
Red rover, red rover, send that girl right over
Goodbye, bystander
We keep walking
Even if at the end of this road isn't Heaven or anything like that
I just want to keep being with you and smiling together
Pride, wishes, and hope
I'll always have them just like you do
When you're scared, so scared, and becoming depressed
I'll protect you, I'll always protect you with everything I have
I promise you to your face
Moonlight
（桐山(きりやま) 零(れい)）あっ
Don't touch me.
（幸田香子(こうだきょうこ)）触らないで
でも 離れないで
But don't move away from me.
Kyouko was like a glass that had cracks in it.
（零）香子は ヒビの入った
グラスみたいな女の子だった
いくら水を注いでも
決して満たされることはなく
No matter how much water you poured into it,
it would never be filled.
She has a family, is blessed with good looks,
and possesses the power to control the people around her.
家族もいて 容姿にも恵まれ—
周りの人間を 支配する力も
持っているのに
And yet,
それでも—
like an animal that's always starving, loneliness ate into her heart.
いつも 飢えた獣みたいに
寂しさに むしばまれていた
そして…
And the ones who put those cracks into her glass were none other than...
そのグラスに ヒビを入れたのは
他の誰でもなく—
my adoptive father...
父親と… 僕だった
and myself.
I'm leaving home.
（香子）家を出るわ
あの人が好きなの
I'm in love with him.
That guy is no good.
（零）ダメだよ あの人は
奥さんがいるんだよ
He has a wife.
ずっと 入院してるわ
She's been in the hospital forever.
あの人 ずっと独りぼっちなのよ
He's been alone all this time.
（零）父さんが許さないよ
Dad won't forgive you if you do this.
（香子）それが 何？
So what?
I don't forgive him either.
許さないのは こっちも同じよ
I haven't forgotten.
忘れないわ
He branded his own daughter a failure when she was just an eighth grader.
たった中２で 娘に—
人生の落後者の
レッテルを貼り付けたのよ
“将棋以外の人生もあるさ”なんて
He told me, "There are other things in life than shogi,"
when he didn't even mean it.
心にもないこと言って
But it's true.
（零）それは 本当だよ
Shogi isn't everything.
将棋だけが 全てじゃないよ
（香子）うそつくんじゃないわよ
Don't lie to me!
Shogi is the only thing you and Dad think about.
あんたも父さんも
将棋しか頭の中にないくせに
もう たくさんなの
I've had enough already.
Both of you look at me like I'm a loser.
二人して あたしのこと—
負け犬でも見るような目で見て
You tiptoe around me.
腫れ物に触るみたいに扱って
It's infuriating.
イライラするの
How long do I have to...
あたし いつまでこんな…
feel this pathetic?
惨めな気持ちで いればいいの？
I'll leave.
僕が 出ていくよ
No matter where I go, no one will worry about me.
僕なら どこへ行っても
心配する人はいないから
But it's different with you, Sis.
でも 姉さんは違う
You're important to Dad...
父さんが 姉さんのこと…
even if you think otherwise.
大事じゃないわけが
ないじゃないか
Thus it is best to have an experienced guide.
（教師）あらまほしき事なり…
10:00 a.m.
（零）午前10時
The match is starting.
対局が始まる
獅子王戦
挑戦者決定トーナメント決勝戦
The finals of the tournament to determine the challenger for the Lion King title.
The first match of three.
三番勝負の初戦
今頃 特別対局室で—
Right now, in the special match room,
those two are quietly facing each other.
あの二人が 静かに…
向かいあっている
I wonder what kind of fight it'll be.
一体 どんな戦いになるのだろう
When I was playing against Shimada,
I was overcome with a strange sensation.
僕は 島田さんと
対局してるとき—
不思議な感覚に襲われた
I felt like I'd stepped into a sea of trees.
樹海に 踏み込んでしまったような
Like I'd become enmeshed in something overpowering.
圧倒的な何かに
絡め取られてゆくような
Like something was silently tightening around me.
音も無く
静かに締め付けられてゆくような
What kind of strategy will he use against Gotou?
彼は 後藤(ごとう)に対して
どんな勝負に出るのだろうか
Faculty Office
Mr. Hayashida, I have my absence notices for March.
先生 ３月分の欠席届を…
Oh, Kiriyama.
（林田高志(はやしだたかし)）ああ 桐山
Look at this. It's incredible.
見てみろ すげぇぞ
Two hours in and this is where they're at.
（林田）開始２時間で これだよ
これ… は…
This is...
Just by looking at the moves played so far,
（零）そこまでの
数手を見ただけで—
重い骨と骨の ぶつかり合う—
it felt like I could hear the dull sound of heavy bones colliding with each other.
鈍い音が 聞こえた気がした
I wondered how those two solemn
guys would play against each other.
重厚が売りの二人が
どう出るかと思ったら—
But it looks like a slugfest.
ガチンコの殴り合いときたもんだ
Man, that's crazy.
いやー きてるなぁ
行ってくれば？
Why don't you go?
あっ… えっ？ どこへ？
Huh? Go where?
The shogi hall.
将棋会館
But...
（零）あっ でも
タイトル戦じゃないから
更新不定期なんだ このブログ
It isn't a title match, so this blog updates irregularly.
Wouldn't it be a better learning experience if you watched it directly?
直接 行ってみた方が
勉強になるんじゃないか？
But I've got so many absences...
（零）でも 出席日数が…
イタッ
Ow!
It's fine! Just go!
（林田）いいから 行け！
Attendance Records
H-He has enough, right?
た… 足りてるよね
Attendance Records
Thump
One, two, three...
ひい ふう みい えーと…
ギリギリセーフだよねぇ
Thump
Um...
Just barely, right?
俺 ひょっとして 教師失格？
Am I not qualified to be a teacher?!
Shogi
Hall
Hey, Kiriyama.
（三角(みすみ)龍雪(たつゆき)）よう 桐山
Kiriyama.
（二海堂(にかいどう)晴信(はるのぶ)）桐山
He made a move.
（三角）あっ 指した
G3b-4c?
（棋士Ａ）４三金(きん)左？
No way. I've never seen Shimada like this before.
うそだろ こんな島田さん
見たことねえよ
What?
えっ！
ここで 角(かく) 捨てんのかよ
Is he throwing away his bishop here?
I've never seen him play like this before either.
俺だって こんな兄者(あにじゃ)
見たことないよ
It felt like their presence had passed from the special match room,
（零）特別対局室から
暗い廊下を伝わって—
through the dark hallway, and seeped into this room.
二人の気配が この部屋まで
にじみ込んでくる気がした
What is it?
（零）何だ？
How? What's different?
どこが… 何が違うんだ？
Why does each move draw me in?
一手 一手に どうして
こんなに引き込まれる
かけてきた時間の長さか
Is it the amount of time they've spent?
積み重ねた経験の厚さか
The depth of their accumulated experience?
The weight of their sacrifices?
引き換えにしてきたものの重さか
それとも それ全部か
Or is it all of that?
That's right. This is...
そうだ これは…
a battle between two people...
自分を信頼している
人間同士の—
戦いなのだ
who have faith in themselves.
終局は ９時
The match ended at 9:00 p.m.
After 153 moves, Shimada, 8-dan, conceded.
153手で 島田八段の投了
The first of three matches in the final of the Lion King Tournament qualifier
獅子王戦—
決勝トーナメント
三番勝負の初戦は まず—
ended with victory for Gotou, 9-dan.
後藤九段の 白星で
幕が上がった
零？
Rei.
This place hasn't changed.
変わんないわね ここ
Such a dreary building.
辛気くさい建物…
I used to hate it.
大嫌いだった
I hated this dark street too.
この暗い通りも
ジメジメした神社も
And the gloomy shrine.
Sis...
姉さん…
Hey.
（後藤正宗(まさむね)）よお
Well, well. If it isn't my two stalkers.
これは これは
ストーカーがおそろいで
Kyouko, what are you doing here?
香子 なんで来た？
I mean...
（香子）だって…
And you were so excited to play against me.
お前さ 俺に当る気
満々だったけどさぁ
What do you think?
どうだった？ 島田 強かったろ
Shimada was really good, right?
Don't underestimate someone in Class A.
Ａ級 なめてんじゃねえぞ
Hey. Are you really leaving?
（香子）ねえ
ほんとに出ていくの？
I didn't want to move away.
（零）離れたくなかった
Hey, wait!
（香子）ねえ 待って
Are you running away from me?
（香子）逃げるんだ あたしから
But I couldn't be with her anymore.
（零）でも もう
一緒にはいられなかった
早く 大人になりたかった
I was in a hurry to become an adult.
I thought if I couldn't stand on my own two feet,
自分の足で立てるように
ならなければ…
there was no way I could protect...
大事な人たちを…
the people I care about.
守れないと思ったから
（島田 開(かい)）あーあ 負けた
I lost.
When I tried to take the initiative with the one-turn loss bishop exchange,
一手損角換(いってぞんかくが)わりで
先手を取ろうとしたら—
that bastard fought back right away.
あんにゃろ
即 応戦してきやがった
And he was cheerful about it!
喜々として！
やっぱ 強(つえ)えーや
あの おっさん
That old man really is tough.
怖(こえ)えーし 顔
And his face is scary.
But on top of being really good, he's not very mature.
強(つえ)え上に 更に大人気もねえ
でも 次は絶対に負けない
Still...
I swear I won't lose next time.
Right!
はい
もちろんです 兄者
Of course, Big Brother!
Moonlight
Lump of Ego
I see...
Crescent Moon
（川本(かわもと)相米二(そめじ)）なるほどなぁ
Blush
I wouldn't have been able to visit either.
そりゃ 来られないわー
うん うん
Full of vigor in front of you girls,
but he sunk before getting to the main event?
娘っ子の前で
そんな たんか切っといて—
本命の前で 撃沈だろ？
Well, you know!
そんな お前…
男子として それはなぁ
For a boy, that's...
Seems to be recalling
different happenings
from his youth
Seems to be recalling
different happenings
from his youth
Seems to be recalling
different happenings
from his youth
Twitch
Fidget
If it were me, I'd slit my belly.
Twitch
Fidget
（従業員Ａ）
俺だったら 腹切るねぇ
Twitch
Fidget
Well, I'd shave off one eyebrow and seclude myself in the mountains.
（従業員Ｂ）
俺なら 片眉そり落として
山に籠るねぇ
Twitch
Fidget
Is it really something that shameful?
（川本(かわもと)ひなた）そんな…
かっこ悪いことかなあ
He doesn't have to worry about it.
気にすること 全然ないのに
He said he would do his best,
and knowing Rei, I'm sure he did.
頑張るって口に出して—
本当に頑張ったんだと思う
零ちゃんなら
Even if it didn't work out, no one would laugh at him.
それでダメだったとしても
誰も笑わないのに
そのとおり
恥なんて かいてなんぼだ
You're right.
Shame has value too.
失敗したってことは
挑戦したってことだからな
Because failing means he took on a challenge.
That's hell of a lot better than a life of doing nothing and laughing at other people.
何にもやんねえで
他人のこと笑ってる人生より—
ずーと まともだ
The thing is, the kid's still young and too damn serious.
ただ 坊主はまだ若いし
くそ真面目だからなあ
He must really have wanted to beat that player.
（川本あかり）よっぽど勝ちたい
相手だったんでしょうね
That was the first time I ever saw Rei show such fighting spirit.
零君が あんなふうに
闘争心を見せたことって—
一度もなかったもの
Well, I suppose he bit off more than he could chew.
まあ そこに目が
行きすぎちまたんだろうな
また 菓子パンとラーメンばっか
食べてるんだろうな
I bet he's eating just sweet bread and ramen.
What should we do at a time like this?
どうしたらいいんだろう
こういうとき
You just gotta leave him be.
ほっとくしかあるめえよ
仕事でかいた恥は—
The only way to make up for a blunder at work is at work.
仕事で取り返すほか
ねえからなあ
Until the kid can think, "I made good,"
all he can do is his best.
坊主が自分で
取り返したって思えるまで—
自分で頑張るしかないだろう
Well, eventually, when he becomes an adult,
he'll realize it, like it or not.
なあに そのうち大人になりゃ
嫌でも気付くさ
That out of all the people who've put themselves out there,
どんなやつでも
一線でやってる人間で—
every single one has been humiliated at some point.
恥をかいたことのないやつなんて
いねえってことにな
島田　お前さ 何か最近…
You know, Shimada, recently,
you look older than me.
俺より年上に見えねえ？
Sure you're not looking in a mirror?
（島田）どこ見てんすか？
It must be tough maintaining that muscular chest.
そっちこそ その胸板
維持するの大変そうっすよね
Have you secretly been hitting the gym?
ひっそりとジム通いですか？
Narcissists have it rough.
大変っすねえ ナルシストは
All right, then.
さて… と
Shall we go?
行きますか
That was cool!
（松本(まつもと)一砂(いっさ)）かっけーなあ
What was that mature presence?!
何だろ あの大人の風格
何 話してんだろ？
I wonder what they were saying!
Big Brother is so cool!
兄者 カッコいいー
Class A, huh?
Ａ級か
If you get into Class A, do you naturally exude that?
Ａ級になれば
自然に醸し出されるのか
おかしいな
まだ みじんもにおわねえ…
Strange. I can't smell the slightest bit of it from myself.
風格が
Right now I'm B-1, but if I move up to Class A,
will I suddenly smell like that?
俺 今 Ｂ１だけど—
Ａ級になったら
いきなり香るのか？
I bet you will! I bet it'll be like an aura!
香んじゃね？
きっと醸されるんじゃね？
Well, let's go!
（二海堂）さっ 行きましょう
Their match is going to start!
対局 始まっちゃいますよ
香んないんじゃないかな
君たち
I don't think you guys ever will have "it."
Not as long as you spy on people from behind bushes.
そんな 草むらから
のぞいてるかぎり
At the end of World War I, as you can see, the strong recovery of productivity...
（教師）
第１次世界大戦が終わり—
この辺りから諸列強の
生産力が回復すると…
（零）10時 対局が始まる
10:00... The match is starting.
獅子王戦
挑戦者決定三番勝負
Three matches to determine the challenger for the Lion King.
一局目は 後藤九段の勝利
Gotou, 9-dan, won the first match.
Shimada is on the ropes now.
島田さんには もう後がない
In the previous match,
they did the unexpected and engaged in a slugfest,
前回は 意表を突いて—
ガチンコの殴り合いだったけど
but what kind of battle will it be this time?
今回は どんな戦いになるんだろう
見たい
I want to watch it.
I want to watch it so badly.
見たくてたまらない
But...
だけど…
Okay! I finished calculating your days of attendance.
（林田）さあ 出席日数の
計算結果が出ましたよ〜
Attendance Records
Bam
And I've come to the conclusion that you
can't catch a cold or even get appendicitis.
はい もう風邪を引くことも—
盲腸になることも
できないことが判明しました
あと２回は 順位戦で
休むことが決まっているから—
You've got two scheduled days off for class-promotion matches, so we can't do anything about that.
それは しかたないとして
But if you happen to advance in any of the tournaments,
you'll be in real danger.
万が一 どれかトーナメントで—
１個でも勝ち進んじゃうと
崖っぷちです
ああ それと
何かあったときのために—
Also, in case something happens,
aim to get above-average scores on your finals.
学年末のテストは なるべく
平均点越え目指してね
As for which parts to study for the tests,
それと…
テストの範囲なんだけど—
if I said, "Ask a friend!" the tests would be over and you'd still be looking for a friend.
友だちに聞けって言うと—
友だち探してる間に
試験終わっちゃうから
先生 代わりに全部の先生に
聞いといてあげたから
So instead, I asked all of the teachers on your behalf.
Here. Don't lose it.
はい しっかりね
It'll be tough if you have to repeat a year.
つらいぞー ２回ダブリは…
Your classmates might call you "old man"!
同級生に おっさんて
呼ばれちゃうかもなんだぞ！
You're right. I know.
そのとおりです ほんとに
This is a big help.
助かります
But what is this feeling?
（零）でも…
何だろう この気持ち
Shogi Hall
Meanwhile...
In the special match room...
Boom
A slugfest. Another one.
（三角）
ガチンコだよ またしても
They're locked together even more than last time.
また もろにガップリだよ
In fact, they're using even more brute force this time.
…っていうか
前回より 更に力任せだよ
Bam
For some reason,
everyone is sitting up straight...
Bang
Slap
Bam
And so, eight hours later...
On top of that...
しかも… ああ！
both of them are entering their kings into the fray!
よりによって 両者入玉(にゅうぎょく)だよ
もう やめようよ！
大人気ないよー
Please stop! That's immature!
“こうなりゃ 入玉しときゃ
勝ちじゃん”みたいなの—
Who thinks, "Since it's come to this,
I'll win if I play the king"?
どうなのそれ？
That was thunder!
（三角）雷 鳴ってるよ
It's no time to be laughing at glowing pieces!
駒が光ってるどころの
騒ぎじゃねえ！
And three more hours later...
Stagger
I won, kiddo.
勝ったぜ 坊
Yes!
はい 兄者　お見事でした
That was awesome, Big Brother!
た… たった一局で…
A-After just one match?
*Youngsters
afraid of the
magnitude
of what's
been lost
*Youngsters
afraid of the
magnitude
of what's
been lost
（松本･横溝）ヒィ…
What's wrong, kiddo?
（島田）どうした？ 坊
ああ いえ
Oh, nothing.
Just that Kiriyama hasn't replied to my text.
桐山から返信がなくて…
I see.
そっかあ
Maybe I went a little too far knocking his lights out.
かち割りすぎちゃったかなあ
あんとき
Tell me, kiddo.
Shogi
Hall
（島田）坊は さあ
Why are you so interested in having Kiriyama get better?
何で そんな桐山に
よくしてやろうとするんだ？
Kiriyama...
桐山は…
Kiriyama is the one...
桐山こそが…
who split my head in half, then pulled me from the mud.
僕の頭を かち割って—
泥の中から出してくれたと
思うからです
I spent a lot of time in the hospital ever since I was little.
小さいころから—
病院で過ごすことが
多かった自分には…
盤上で 強くなることだけが—
Getting better in front of a shogi board was my sole emotional support.
心を支える 全てでした
While watching my peers having fun and
playing outside from the corner of my eye,
そうやって
同年代のみんなが—
楽しく外で
遊び回っているのを—
I would keep myself immersed in shogi.
横目で 見ながら—
将棋だけに 没頭を続けて
46th Children's
Shogi Tournament
And yet, the better I got,
なのに強くなれば なるほど—
the more I wrote off my weaker opponents as cowards who didn't even bother making an effort.
弱い対戦相手が 全て—
努力を放棄した
ひきょう者に思えて
It was so frustrating and annoying and irritating.
悔しくて
腹が立ってイライラして
Then, after being reduced to a lump of ego...
そんな 自我のカタマリに
成り果てていたとき
（零）あの… これ
Um... here.
Water.
水
I met Kiriyama,
（二海堂）僕は…
桐山に 出会って—
he split my head in half,
頭を かち割られて—
and he saved me.
救われたんです
"Oh, there's someone better than me."
ああ 俺より強いやつがいる
"There's someone who worked harder than me."
俺より 努力した人間がいる
I realized I wasn't alone.
俺は 独りぼっちじゃ
ないんだって
I see.
そっか
Yeah.
うん　分かるよ
I kind of understand what you mean.
何となく… それ
Wait a second!
（香子）
ちょっと待ってよ ねえ！
Hey!
（香子）ねえったら ねえ！
I said, hey!
What the hell?! Gotou, you moron!
何よ 後藤のバカー！
もう知らないんだからね
I'm done with you!
Hey...
ちょっ おま… 後藤
確か 妻帯…
Gotou, what are you...
Wait, isn't he married...
Who's that beautiful... and... young...
誰？ それ 美人じゃん
しかも若っ！
What was that? An argument?
何でしょうね ケンカかな？
何だろう この敗北感…
What is this sense of defeat?
No, that was nothing!
いいや 何のまだこれしき
Swing
Dammit! I swear I'll win the next one too!
くそっ もう… 絶対 次も勝つ！
Come on, kiddo. Let's get back and plan a strategy for the final match!
さあ 坊 早速帰って
次の対策 練りまくるぞ！
Yay! There it is! That's the Big Brother I know!
（二海堂）わーい さすが
それでこそ 兄者です
Meanwhile, over to Kiriyama...
Mr. Hayashida found
a grave miscalculation.
Filling in the gaps
with many reports
I'm sorry. You were actually already two days short.
ごめん　すでに
２日足りてなかったぁ…
That's okay, Mr. Hayashida.
（零）いえ… 先生—
Really, it's like...
何か ほんとにもう…
Lump of Ego
すみません
I'm the one who's sorry.
Your fingers, your chest, your eyes
Are so dazzling there are nights when I get dizzy
They suddenly fall upon me, and it's just so warm
That it feels like I swallowed a seven-colored star
You held me tight, troubling me like a burning spark would
But I was taught to keep walking despite everything
God, please hear me out
For just a little while
Please connect us like that constellation
So that we're never away from each other
So that we're always together
Next Episode Preview
Episode 16
Okay, what shall we do for this year's Girls' Day Festival at our house?
（あかり）さーてと
我が家の今年のひな祭りは
何にしましょうか
Well, shall we get started?
（島田）それじゃあ
ぼちぼち始めますか
Oops! I forgot the original purpose!
（林田）あー いっけねえ
本題忘れてた
If he never comes to
visit anymore, then fine.
（ひなた）いつまでも来ないと
もう 知らないからね
Let's hurry and eat some
fried tofu pouches!
（モモ）おいなりさん
早く早く 食べたいなあ
Illustration: Yamazaki Mari
"March comes in like a lion."
（香子）３月のライオン
ちょっと 後藤
Hey, Gotou, you'd better watch it too.
あんたも ちゃんと
見るんだからね
（後藤）わーったよ
I know, already!
You guys better not miss it either.
お前らも 見逃すんじゃねーぞ